[Music]
How's it going everyone? In this video,
we are going to talk about protected
swings or protected highs and lows in
the market. So, let's get into the
video. So, what is a protected swing? A
protected swing is a high or low in
which I'm expecting to hold as the trend
continues. So what do I mean by that? In
this case, in a bullish scenario, I'm
expecting this low to remain intact if
this trend is going to continue higher.
Now, how do I define a protected high or
low or a protected swing? Well, there
are two types and this would be the
first one. If we are bullish, I want to
see a low or a short-term low be ran out
or swept and then close through the
series of downclo candles that made the
low. So, you can see here, here is the
low. we find the series of downclo
candles. I mark that out once price
closes over that level. This is now a
protected low and I expect it to hold if
we're going to continue higher. Now,
when do we not need to run out the low?
Well, that is only if we use SMT. So, in
this case, using SMT, the correlated
asset has ran out the low forming a
protected low. So, then we can
anticipate this low to hold as well. So
in this case, I'll use the series of
downclosed candles that made the failure
swing. Once that is closed over, then
expecting these to hold here. Now the
other type of protected swing is one
formed out of a fair value gap. So in
the first two examples, it is based off
of a high or low being swept out. In
this case, it is price reaching into a
fair value gap. I then find the low. I
found this series of downcloed candles
that form that low. Once price closes
over that level, I then anticipate this
low to hold if price is going to
continue
higher. So let's get into an example
here. You can see price is trending down
into an important level where we may
anticipate a new phase of price. You can
see we have series of downlosed candles
into that important level. Do we close
over those two downlosed candles? No. So
it is still bearish. So, taking a look
here now, we have swept out that
short-term low or sweeping out a
liquidity point. Here we have the
correlated asset to show you what it
looks like with an SMT, but we're going
to focus on this one. But now, with the
sweep of a low, we can find this low,
find the series of down close candles
that made that low. Go ahead and mark
out this level. And when price closes
over that level, this low is now
protected. Or anticipate this low to
hold. if price is going to reverse and
change trend and continue higher. So
from here I can look to take an entry or
seek a continuation as I'm expecting
this trend to continue higher. So let's
get into some examples in trading
view. So here we are with our first
example and you can see we have had
expansion lower and then we're having a
consolidation. So if you understand the
phases of price, if we are in a
consolidation, where do we want to
focus? The external parts of the range.
Since we are bearish, what would we want
to see? We would want to see highs ran
out to then trade back lower. So taking
a look at this, what happens when we
reach up into this high? Well, we sweep
it out. And if you notice, we have a
candle to closure, or if you see my
daily bias video, we're closing back
inside the previous day's range. So, we
can expect this to trade lower. Let's go
down to the hourly chart to see what
this looks like. So, here we are down on
the hourly chart and I have my indicator
up with the daily candles so you can
visualize it. Here we have swept out our
previous day's high. And do we form a
reversal? Well, what forms a protected
high? Well, let's say I was trying to
frame a reversal off of this previous
day high. We have that turtle soup. But
what happens and why do I wait for a
protected high? Well, we never get that
confirmation of the close through the
series of downclosed candles that made
that high. So, you can see how it just
fails. Now, we have another sweep over
this high. What happens here? Well, do
we get a closure through the series of
candles that made the high? In this
case, it is just one. Yes, we do. So,
with this now, we can anticipate this
trend to have flipped and we are
bearish, right? And what does this do?
This is now a protected swing, right?
I'm expecting this high to remain intact
because it has been closed through if
price is going to continue bearish. So,
I'm expecting this wick to remain intact
as we trade lower. So, getting into the
next day, let's see what happens. You
can see my indicator does plot a bearish
signal. We reach up into here and
there's really not much going on here as
this is a whole series up. I would be
ignoring this small little candle there.
What happens if we need a protected
swing? We would need what? A high to be
swept out. Why are we looking for a high
to be swept out and not a low? Well, we
are bearish because this trend is now
bearish as long as this wick remains
intact. So, now that we have swept out
the high, what would we need to form a
protected swing right here to trade off
of? We would need this series of upclose
candles that swept out that high to be
closed below. So, as we let this
continue, do we get a closure below
that? We do right here. So, now I'm
expecting this high to remain, but we
have a new protected high. I'm expecting
this high to remain. And due to the day,
I'm expecting that to remain intact as
we continue into the next day, pretty
late into the session. So, here we are
in the next day. We have a
consolidation. Here we sweep out this
high. What would we need for price to
form a protected high right here? We'd
need a closure through a series of up
close candles. Not really many series of
up close candles there. So, it would
just be that body right there. So,
marking that out, I would need a closure
through that. We have yet to get that.
Right. So, now we have swept out a new
high. So, I'm just going to repeat the
process. And here you can see where
would be this series of closed candles
right there. So, let's see when we get a
closure through that.
Right there we get the closure through.
So now I'd expect this high to remain
intact. And you can see how this is used
for a continuation of a trend. Here is a
reversal. And each one of these is a
continuation of this bearish trend or a
lower time frame reversal. And where
would I be looking to target? Well, I
have my liquidity points here as marked
out via my indicator. So as we let this
continue, we go and take out that
low. Taking a look. Do we get a
retracement or a reversal? It's looking
like a retracement. What do we have
here? We sweep out a high or into a fair
value gap. And what do we also have? A
closure through the series of upclose
candles into that important level. I
could then anticipate this high to
remain if we're going to continue
lower. And once again, we get a
continuation
lower. We have a very deep retracement
almost taking out this high, but it
remains intact. With that deep
retracement, what do we reach into? a
fair value gap here. And so then now
with the closure through this up close
candle into that fair value gap, we now
have a new protected high, right? And so
all I'm looking for is this low cuz that
is our daily target. Let's see if that
gets taken or if our protected high gets
taken out
first. And you can see we get those lows
taken out. So hopefully that makes sense
how we have a reversal. This forms a
protected high, right? A protected
swing. And then we are expecting this
trend to continue until it is violated
right with daily closures as we are
closing outside the previous day's lows.
So as long as that is occurring I'm
expecting this trend to continue and I
can continue to just track the protected
swings in the market giving me areas
that I want to
sell. So here we are with our same EU
example. We were just up here and we had
those lows taken out down here. Now, if
we're expecting this to continue lower,
what are we looking at? Well, we had
this range high. It's taken out and we
have this range low. Now, we have equal
lows. We have expansion. And we are
consolidating. So, if we're expecting a
continuation lower, what do we want to
see? A run of a high and then to form a
protected swing. Now, let's talk about
something. The anticipation of a
protected swing versus a protected swing
forming. So you can see here I have the
narrative that I'm expecting this high
to form in here to trade lower. So I can
anticipate that protected swing to form
and drop down to the hourly chart. And
that is where I could look for lower
time frame setups and confirmations. So
you can see here we have price running
out this high here. We close through the
series of upclose candles into that
high, right? And so I'm expecting a
continuation lower here. So if we have
expansion, what do we expect? either a
retracement or a consolidation to get a
continuation signature. Right here we
are pretty much consolidating and what
do we notice? We are taking out highs,
right? So, we reach into this fair value
gap over here and we don't get that
protected swing, right? We get a very
lethargic move back into the range here,
not confirming this as a protected high.
So, we have another sweep of a high
here. Where would be our protected high?
A closure through here. So, I can go
ahead and wait for that. And when we
close through here, what am I
anticipating? I'm now anticipating this
high to remain intact, which means this
wick high has formed. And I can expect
to trade that lower. So, we let that
continue. We go and take out that
previous day's low. And let's see if we
run out the low. We are currently
leaving this range low.
And then as we approach this candle for
continuation, I'm expecting the lower
half of this candle to push price lower.
We have price running out a high right
here into a fair value gap. Where are
the series of candles? Well, you could
use these bull move here. But if we look
at this, price went up, down, back up.
So I can really just use this level in
here. So let's see what
happens. We run out a new high. That
gives me a new level to look at right
here. Sweep. Not very clean in here, but
I can use that leg up or I could just
use the same level closure through that.
And then we go ahead and drop through
those lows. So, you can see if we go
back out to our daily time frame here.
What we can do is use that narrative on
the daily chart with a daily closure to
anticipate and refine it on the hourly.
Or if we were just going to wait for the
daily setup, we'd have the anticipation
of that swing. And then when we close
through here, that is the confirmation
that this high should remain intact as
we go run out that low and we get an
expansion lower. So here we are on our
next example. ES on the 4hour chart and
we have the daily candles up here. You
can see we have a nice bearish closure
on the daily chart. So if expecting a
continuation lower, I want to see from
the lower half of this. Well, what area
is in the lower half? We have a fair
value gap right here. So, if I'm
expecting price to retrace up and
continue lower, I want to see price form
a high in here to continue lower. So,
letting another candle play out. What
are we left with? Is that a bearish
closure? It is not. So, I can give it
another candle. Is this a bearish
closure? Yes, it is. We sweep out our
previous and we close back inside the
range. So, with this, I can drop down to
the 15-minute chart. So, here we are
down on the 15-minute chart. And do we
have a protected swing? Well, we find
this high right here. We find the series
of upclose candles that made it. Have we
closed through it? Yes, we have. So,
with that, I'm expecting this high to
remain intact. Now, as we move ahead,
what happens? Do we have any points of
interest? Well, waiting for the closure
and the open of the new candle. We do
right here as we have swept out this
high. So now what am I seeing? If we're
going to form a new protected high, we
need to close through where? Right here.
Why that point? Because that is the
series of up close candles. In this
case, just one that swept out this
previous high or point of interest. So
as we let this continue, we close
through there. And now I can anticipate
a move lower to that sellside liquidity
point.
So starting out this next example, we
are on silver 1 hour chart. So you can
see our daily chart here, we have a nice
sweep of the highs and closure back in,
which is very bearish. So going ahead
and marking out this up close candle
here. I'd want to see that be respected
as we trade lower. Now with this, where
is our protected swing? Well, my
indicator will mark that out. But I'll
find the high here. I'll find the series
of candles that made that high. In this
case, it is just one as it sweeps out
this high previous as well. And so that
is our protected high. Now, if I'm
looking to take a position in here, do I
want to enter with my stop all the way
on this high? That doesn't really give
good risk-to-reward to my first target
or even to my projections. So, with
that, I'm going to let a new protected
swing form to look for an entry. So, as
I let this play forward, let's see what
happens. Does price reach into a point
of interest? It does as it reaches into
a fair value gap here. And what else do
we have? We have the series of upclose
candles or in this case a singular one
into that point of interest. And we are
now closed through. So now I have a new
protected swing in the market and I'm
expecting this to remain intact as we
trade lower if this trend is going to
continue. So then this is where I can
sell, put my stop on the protected swing
high and then look for 2
R. So let's see how this works
out. And you can see we hit our 2R and
then we go to that first standard
deviation projection. But that is an
example of how I would actually look to
trade with protected swings. I'm using
it as my invalidation. So I want an
entry fairly close to my invalidation to
give me good
risk-to-reward. So here we are in our
next example and you can take a look at
this sell side of the curve here running
out these lows. Here is where we formed
that protected swing as we've closed
through here. 50% is retested and then
we get a continuation lower. Now you can
see all these failure swings on the
highs. Once again we want to be trading
towards failure swings and we want
protected swings on our side of the
market. So we have failure swings on the
buy side of the market. And what do we
notice down here? We have swept out a
low. Have we confirmed that low or
protected that low? Yes. As we have
closed through the series of down close
candles that formed that low. So now I
can anticipate this low to hold. If this
is going to be the low or the reversal
off previous day low to then trade
higher back through these highs. So as
we zoom in, let's see how this forms in
here. So you can see what do we have. We
have a point of interest, a fair value
gap here. We have a down closed candle
into that point of interest. It's then
closed over. So what does that give us?
That gives us a new protected swing,
right? So this would be the continuation
or the order block formed at the
low-risk buy. So once again here, that
is where I could look to buy, put my
stop on the invalidation, and then from
there I could be looking for 2 R, right?
or I could be looking for those highs up
here, right? Because that is where I'm
anticipating price to trade to. So,
let's see what happens as we let this
play out. We get a continuation higher
and we hit our TP up there. So, once
again, it's just important to track
those protected swings because that is
where the opportunities lie. You don't
have to catch them at the reversal. You
can get the continuation or even the
candles following that reversal or when
the continuation is confirmed. Now, I
hope you enjoyed this video. It is a
very important concept within my
trading. So, I hope you find it helpful.
Now, when I am looking for entries, I am
mainly focused on a new invalidation
forming. When I can anticipate a new
invalidation forming or a new protected
swing, that gives me a new area to
anticipate expansion from or to trade
off of. Now, if you have any questions,
feel free to leave them in the comments
below or any suggestions for future
videos. I hope you enjoyed and I'll see
you guys next time. Have a good one.